Welcome back to a push in under 3
minutes. No time for intros. Let's get
into it. In a previous video, I said the
three causes of the guilded age were
westward expansion, the industrial
revolution, and capitalism. We already
covered the West, so now it's time to
talk about the other two. Starting with
the industrial revolution. And when I
say the industrial revolution, I mean
the second industrial revolution. And
even though that's considered a more
European term, with how much
industrialization happened during the
guilded age, it is fair to call what
happened a second industrial revolution.
During the guilded age, all the new
technology led to businesses wanting to
capitalize on the production or rather
the mass production of the goods. There
was a really big workforce because of a
bunch of new immigration and the
government policies heavily favored
businesses. And that is where we get to
throw in a key term, industrial
capitalism. This is where private
individuals own the means of production
like factories and machinery to generate
profit through wage-based labor by
mass-producing goods. Since this would
be popularized, it would mean the
capitalist lzas afair economic system
would become mostly standard in the
United States, meaning that it is the
third cause of the guilded age. Now we
turn to the consequences of this
industrial expansion which facilitated
the rise of three dominant corporate
figures of the guilded age. John D.
Rockefeller, Andrew Carnegie, and JP
Morgan. Rockefeller was probably the
richest man in American history. He
coined horizontal integration where he'd
buy out all of his rivals and he led the
oil industry. Carnegie on the other hand
coined vertical integration where he
controlled each and every means of
production and led the steel industry
and Morgan's the bank guy meaning he
controlled like finance or something.
Stuff like trusts were set up along with
many companies holding stock in other
companies known as holding companies
which resulted in entire industries like
oil and steel to be completely
monopolized and these businesses would
even seek out markets outside of America
in all of these places on the screen.
And this would be the economic prelude
to American imperialism. As for the
government, initially what we see are
weak Supreme Court decisions and the
poorly enforced Sherman Antitrust Act,
which meant the government really
couldn't do anything to combat this
guilded age. And yes, it is definitely
fair to say that these corporate giants
to use their deep pockets to influence
American politics. So, you might ask,
what is the result of all of this? Well,
I'll tell you. This would cause a
disproportionate share of American
wealth to be accumulated amongst a very
few top elite. Small businesses now
don't stand a chance. Monopolies would
cause prices on goods to go up and most
of all workers would be paid horribly in
these factories and had almost no power
to bargain otherwise. Very quickly, this
will cause these quote captives of
industry to be referred to as robber
barons because honestly that is kind of
what they are. This would lead to a
movement later known as progressivism,
but I get ahead of myself. On the screen
now are AP style questions for this
topic. Pause now.
I'll put the answers on the screen now.
I will see you in the next one.